<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of Sr. Humfrey Linde, to a lady of great worth, much afflicted for Syr Humfreys sake, hearing him ill spoke of, for not answering the Whetstone, and the Spectacles, that were written against his Via tuta And also for that he is greatly taxed for lying and corrupting of many authours. In which letter he doth cleare himselfe.</title>
            <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836485</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836485</idno>
            <idno type="VID">762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06632)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1317:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of Sr. Humfrey Linde, to a lady of great worth, much afflicted for Syr Humfreys sake, hearing him ill spoke of, for not answering the Whetstone, and the Spectacles, that were written against his Via tuta And also for that he is greatly taxed for lying and corrupting of many authours. In which letter he doth cleare himselfe.</title>
                  <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
                  <author>Lynde, Humphrey, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M.DC.XXXIIII. [1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire on Lynde, written by J. Floyd?--STC.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:762:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:762:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF S.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> HVMFREY LINDE, To a Lady of great Worth, much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for <hi>Syr Humfreys</hi> ſake, hearing him ill ſpoken of, for not anſwering the <hi>Whetſtone,</hi> and the <hi>Spectacles,</hi> that were written agaynſt his <hi>Via tuta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND Alſo for that he is greatly taxed for <hi>lying,</hi> and <hi>corrupting</hi> of many Authours.</p>
            <p>In which Letter he doth cleare himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Printed Anno M.DC.XXXIIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:762:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:762:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The affliction you endure for my ſake is a ſharpe Arrow, ſhot eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to my hart, and is not thence to be remoued, vntill your griefe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, by this my Letter, which I know, to you (who are ſo zealous a louer of the Word, and hater of the Pope) will giue aboundant ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. As for the Church-going Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts therefore, and ſome other that are not of the purer ſort of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church, who as you ſay, do daſh you in the teeth with my lyes, 150. and odd, in my firſt Booke called <hi>Via tuta,</hi> and the Lord knowes how many in my ſecond, called <hi>Via deuia;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:762:3"/>
ſo that when you would ſound forth my euerlaſting praiſes, they ſtop your pure Mouth, with my infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of corruptions, ſhiftes, <hi>Foxian, Iewellian,</hi> and <hi>Mortonian</hi> falſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; crying out, that I haue had too printed Bookes ſent me, one called the <hi>Spectacles</hi> to ſee my way, the other the <hi>Whetstone,</hi> the iuſt reward of my deſert, for lying ſo egregiouſly, with many other papers of like nature diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing my vntruthes: Know deare Lady, that a Brother, or Siſter that ſpring, from the pure bowels of the reformed Church (as your Honour and I doe) muſt ſuffer much more then this, by that vile, deformed, and Antichriſtian Crew, the Wicked. But now to the matter.</p>
            <p>This only I requeſt at your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours hands, that if you know any ſhould be deſirous (before my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bookes come forth) to receaue any further ſatisfaction then this my Letter to your Ladiſhippe will giue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:762:3"/>
them, they may be ſent on the Lords name either to my owne Houſe, or to the Wine-Office, where I and many of our learned and zealous brethren meete often, about a further refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion: deſiring, that not ſo much as a ragge of Popery, may remayne in the Houſe of the Lord; neither Bells nor Organs, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets or Myters, ſquare Caps, or Surpliſſes, Croſſe or Image: for I am aſſured, a true Brother, or Siſter had rather ſee Antichriſt himſelfe then any of theſe; nay we truſt in the Lord to put the Word <hi>Catholicke,</hi> out of the Creed, as well as out of Tombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, and in place therof, to ſay, I belieue in <hi>the Reformed Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though our enemyes ſhew, that <hi>Lying</hi> is one of the Markes of our Church, and that I for the glory of it, haue told ouer againe all the lyes of <hi>M. Bell, Fox, Iewell, White, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and others in a new faſhion: yet, all this notwithſtanding, I hope to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:762:4"/>
giue any reaſonable man full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>For put caſe, there hath beene now and then a ſlip or two, and that out of the aboundance of my zeale I haue ſometimes ouerlaſhed, or ſtret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched a point for the loue of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; I hope this will be no ſuch Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Crime, amongſt the pure little Flocke, who know right well, what latitude may be vſed for the ſplendor of the Ghoſpell: &amp; what our Elders and Fore-fathers in this kind haue done, no learned knight can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. What therfore I haue done, was not without authority: yea herein I haue tracked the very footſteps of the moſt famous <hi>D. Luther,</hi> and the pure preacher of the word <hi>D. Caluin.</hi> Theſe were the lights ſent from heauen it ſelf to driue away the darke clouds of papiſtry. Theſe were they who made their doctrine odious to the world. And wot you how? why thus: Thoſe reuerend Fathers of our Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:762:4"/>
how Papiſts bragged of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to keep Gods Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without Gods grace; how they put their truſt in their owne Merits, and not in Chriſts; how they adored Bread, Statues, Images, and Idols.</p>
            <p>Now the Papiſts aſhamed, denyed it ſtoutly; Againe, thoſe Reuerend Fathers affirmed it boldly, &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced them. What, is not our affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation a ſufficient refutation of their deniall? Sure I am this manner of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinge hath beene allowed of, this foureſcore yeares in our Churches, and pulpits. When D. Luther (<hi>tom. de matrim. f.</hi> 119.) began to teach (from aboue no doubt) that this in Geneſis <hi>Multiply, and increaſe,</hi> was not a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only, but more then a Precept, and that it was not within the power of a man to be without a woman: And agayne, that if the wife would not yield ſhe ſhould be ſent packing; marry <hi>Hesther</hi> &amp; put away <hi>Vasthi:</hi> &amp; that if the husband were impotent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:762:5"/>
the wife might marry another, or with his conſent lye ſecretly with his brother, or ſome other man: What did the Papiſts? Oh it vexed them to heare of reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they vrged Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture too, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. where it is ſaid; that <hi>Whoſoeuer diſmiſſeth his wife, vnles for fornication, and marieth another, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth adultery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, they haue not the ſpirit of interpreting Scriptures, &amp; their old Fathers, &amp; Grandſires were blinded, and therfore according to his Tenet well ſayth <hi>D. Luther: Be it that the Church, Auguſtine, &amp; other Doctors, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Apollo, yea an Angell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen teach otherwiſe, yet is my doctrine ſuch as ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth Gods only glory.</hi> Nay he had authority from heauen to reprehend the Apoſtles themſelues, and to put in and out what he pleaſed of the holy Word of the Lord: for ſo he himſelfe affirmeth in his booke agaynſt <hi>King Henry</hi> the 8. <hi>I am certayne</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>I have my doctrine from heauen; and yet</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:762:5"/>
marke the humility of the man) <hi>it is not myne</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>but Chriſtes.</hi> And therefore you ſee, how afterwards King <hi>Henry</hi> obeyed him, and his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which he would neuer haue done, had it not beene from God, or had it not beene moſt pure and holy doctrine: and therfore you may read how zealous King <hi>Henry</hi> became, how purely and chaſtly he liued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conuerted from Popery.</p>
            <p>Agayne, D. <hi>Luther</hi> added to the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. this word <hi>alone: Man is iuſtifyed by fayth alone.</hi> And this not without both authority from God, (as before you haue heard out of his owne mouth, and no doubt do firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belieue) but alſo with great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to wit, to vexe the old Papiſts. O this doth ſilence them, this makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chafe and ſweat. Let them cry, we falſify the Scripture: I will ſtudy no further anſwere for them, then this of <hi>D. Luthers</hi> which is neuer to be anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered: <hi>A Papist, and an Aſse, are all one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:762:6"/>
thinge: So I will haue it, ſo I commaund it, my will muſt stand for a reaſon.</hi> And good reaſon, for thy Will was the Lords will, and the Lords will was thy Will. So in the 2. of <hi>Peter</hi> he hath thruſt out <hi>good Workes,</hi> as not beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming theſe holy times, when a liuely fayth excludeth all good Workes; all counſels of Pouerty, Chaſtity, and Obedience. Giue me fayth, and let the Papiſts goe with their good Works, and Reſtitutions whither they will. Ile none.</p>
            <p>This doctrine we exactly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and proteſt neuer to do good worke ſo long as we breath. Heere you ſee my grounds for it out of this prophet, ſent from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reforme the world; and you ſee alſo that we may iuſtly alter the text, and vſe our wits in clearing of the Scripture, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying our doctrine, and deluding the Papiſtes.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit another Prophet <hi>D. Caluin,</hi> ſo named by himſelfe: <hi>I am
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:762:6"/>
a Propheth</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>I haue the ſpirit of God &amp;c.</hi> thus, full of zeale in his 4. booke of <hi>Institutions cap.</hi> 12. and elſe where. Now marke the ſpirit &amp; zeale of this man. In the preface of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, he tells vs that the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of <hi>Baſill,</hi> was a lawfull Councell, and perſiſted in full authority and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the end. Now then, he proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth moſt learnedly, that the Papiſt Church hath fayled: for that Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell depoſed <hi>Eugenius</hi> and choſe <hi>Felix;</hi> yet the Councell being ended, <hi>Eugenius</hi> ſtole againe into the chayre without any Canonicall election; and ſo from him (a falſe Pope) all the ſucceeding Popes haue ſprunge, making euer ſince a falſe Church.</p>
            <p>Thus that rare &amp; eminent ſtarre <hi>Iohn Caluin,</hi> whoſe wiſedom thought it not conuenient in thoſe times to be ſo fooliſhly ſcrupulous, as to ſpeake truth, and to lay open, that indeed it was firſt a true Councell, but after when it depoſed <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and choſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:762:7"/>
               <hi>Felix,</hi> it was a diabolicall &amp; ſeditious Councell, ſo called by the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councell, <hi>Seſsione</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Now in verity tell me, what zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man is there of ours that doth not follow this example of <hi>M. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin?</hi> And who will not, to defend an article of our Fayth (to wit, <hi>That the Church may erre</hi>) diſſemble, or equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate, I will not ſay lye? though the Scripture ſay, <hi>Omnis homo mendax, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man is a lyar,</hi> which muſt be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſomtimes eſpecially in neceſſity: and when is there more neceſſity then for the Ghoſpell, to vexe the Papiſts that cry for truth and playne dealing forſooth? Yes, with them, who hate vs, and would deſtroy the Ghoſpell.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>M. Caluin,</hi> who can once doubt but that he had a reuelation to deale thus with the Pope. In his third booke of Inſtitutions <hi>cap.</hi> 20. he ſaith, The Papiſts in their hymnes and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanies neuer make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of Chriſt, but pray alwayes to dead men. This
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:762:7"/>
doctrine our men teach alſo in their Pulpits, taken, as you ſee, from <hi>M. Caluin.</hi> This mads the Papiſts, calling vs <hi>falſifiers, vntrue dealers &amp;c.</hi> and that this is one of our ordinary lies, becaus they ſay in their Letanies, <hi>Lord haue mercy on vs: Christ haue mercy on vs: God the Father of heauen, haue mercy on vs &amp;c.</hi> Alas this is only a poore ſhift, put only for a ſhew: but let them talke in the meane tyme what they will; ſo long as the contrary is preached in our pulpits, this makes the papiſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious amongſt the people. Agayne in the ſame place he ſayth: <hi>They inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Saints as Gods.</hi> They deny it. <hi>Caluin</hi> and all our Brethren affirme it. One <hi>Caluin,</hi> one <hi>Melancthon,</hi> one Miniſter of the Lord is to be belieued before a thouſand Papiſts, though it be in a point of their owne Religion.</p>
            <p>I muſt let paſſe for breuity ſake infinite other of our Ancients, that haue giuen vs good example how to deale with the Pope; and for my part
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:762:8"/>
I haue not beene backward like a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly diſciple to follow their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, neyther will as long as I liue.</p>
            <p>But now let vs looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our own learned Countrymen, in this buſines of ſo great importance. God be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there are ſo many I know not where to beginne: Pitty it is I muſt leaue moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out, or elſe I ſhould make a volume as big as <hi>Iohn Foxes</hi> Acts and Monuments, that graue, ſimple, and vpright man, who is ſo falſly accuſed by that crafty Ieſuite <hi>Parſons,</hi> for telling in his Acts a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand lyes, and in three leaues 120. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue him who pleaſe, for ile be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged firſt, vnleſſe ſome of our owne Congregation will take the paines to ſhew me them.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I will beginne with Biſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> a man of famous memory for deluding the Papiſts ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. In his booke called <hi>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence pag.</hi> 7. he ioyneth the Manichees and Papiſtes togeather, both for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:762:8"/>
Marriage, and allowing of Fornication. The Papiſts are madd, deny it, and eſteeme it blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Church, condemne his proofes as falſe, which he brings out of <hi>Panormitan,</hi> and others, who only affirme, that Fornication was not puniſhed now ſo rigorouſly as in the primitiue times; &amp; from thence they infer, that the Biſhop hath iniured, &amp; belyed their doctrine, &amp; falſified <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitan:</hi> and this they ſay, in him is plaine. But what ſaith the <hi>Iewel?</hi> Alas, he counts this anſwere as ridiculous.</p>
            <p>Agayne <hi>D. Harding,</hi> a notable old Papiſt, affirmes, he hath conuinced him of hundreds of lyes: But were there tyme, I could ſhew you how brauely he comes off, of all. Tuſh let the Papiſtes ſay what they pleaſe, we will ſay with <hi>Paul.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>We are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led deceauers, and yet we ſay truth.</hi> The Reuerend Doctour &amp; Bishop aforſaid in another place obiects againſt them their priuate, or ſole Communion.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:762:9"/>
The Papiſts anſwere diuers wayes, out of the ancient Fathers, Baſill, and the monkes of Aegypt, and I know not where. But after all their labour, marke, I beſeech you, how wittily the <hi>Iewell</hi> anſwereth, and confuteth them, pittying their poore proofes: <hi>If</hi> ſaith he, <hi>M. Harding could find any thing in the Church, he would not thus hunt after the mountaynes, and flye for ayd into Egipt, if he could find it neerer home.</hi> Was not this a wiſe anſwere, for ſo farre fetch a proofe?</p>
            <p>Againe, the Papiſts, forſooth, will not haue their Church to erre, God muſt take heed of breaking his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with them, and they hould him to it. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. <hi>The gates of hell shall neuer preuayle against it. I will be with you, till the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world. The holy Ghost shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne with you for euer,</hi> with like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities out of Scriptures, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Fathers, and they thinke to kill it dead. But marke the <hi>Iewell</hi> in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:762:9"/>
this point how he anſwereth <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. You papists</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſay it stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des not with Gods promiſe to forſake his Church a thouſand yeares together</hi> (now he plyes them;) <hi>It is not much for you openly the breake Gods commaundements, to defyle his holy ſanctuary, to turne light into darkenes, and yet neuertheles you will not sticke to binde him to his promiſe.</hi> Here you ſee the Conſciences of the Papiſts; they may breake their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, tranſgreſſe the Law, offende their God, but God muſt not breake with them. See how diuinely this learned Biſhow quelleth the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his importune aduerſaries. An anſwere it is, certainly inſpired by the Lord of truth, and that of our Truth, and not by the Deuill, as the Romaniſts ſay.</p>
            <p>Well, I am ſorry I muſt leaue out infinite places of this reuerend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, by which he hath taught me, and many others, to deale with the papiſts as they deſerue, but he is dead
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:762:10"/>
&amp; gone, &amp; no doubt rewarded for his labours: we wil no more of the dead, but of the liuing, &amp; thoſe no ſmal foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les I can tell you, both in their owne &amp; our eyes. Appeare then in thy like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes graue <hi>D. White,</hi> as thy picture ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth thee in thy laſt worke. But now that is changed together with thy ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, for thou art a Biſhop, and that well deſeruing it, &amp; that not for thy Lying, as the Papiſts pretend, but for thy witty writings againſt thoſe thy inueterate Enemies, as I ſhall make appeare moſt manifeſtly.</p>
            <p>Obſerue therfore, O honourable Lady, how wittily he brings their owne authors, their Cardinalls, and Fathers againſt themſelues. And firſt Cardinall <hi>Hoſius,</hi> in his <hi>expreſſo verbo Dei, Expreſſe word of God,</hi> who (as the Biſhop relateth in his reply to the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite Fiſher <hi>page</hi> 15. in the end, and <hi>page</hi> 152. in the beginning) hath this doctrine: <hi>A man ought not to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scriptures, but taught of God: it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:762:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is labour lost to ſpend time in Scripture, for it is but a creature, yea an empty ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it becomes not a Chriſtian to be conuerſant in Scripture.</hi> Madame is not here Blaſphemy? doth not the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour iuſtly inſult here ouer the Pope and the Ieſuits his Bandoggs, that barke continually againſt the pure louers of the Word, who had rather ſee the diuell then a Ieſuite or a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſt, which I thanke the Lord for, I euer thought to be monſters, I was ſo purely educated in the houſe of the Lord, euer harkening diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how eloquently our Miniſters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually reuiled them; ſo that I haue beene bred vp with a holy hatred to them, and with pure eyes lifted vp to heauen, I prayſe the Lord for it, I ſtill hate them as zealouſly, as the good Recorder of <hi>Salisbury</hi> did the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God the Father, which he va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly brake in pieces, although his legge, &amp; almoſt his necke was broken for it, out of malice infallibly of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:762:11"/>
deuill for his doing ſo good a deed.</p>
            <p>But now to the anſwere of the Papiſts againſt the Doctour. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth they ſay, this doctrine is not theirs, and that <hi>Hoſius</hi> hath not theſe wordes of his owne, but relates them as the blaſphemous wordes of the <hi>Swinckfeldian</hi> Sect, called the <hi>Heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets, Swinckfeldius</hi> a Hater of Fryars and Monkes being their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, and reprehends and cenſures them. Yea <hi>Hoſius</hi> himſelfe being taxed therwith by ſome learned men of ours in his life time, anſwers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſame, and ſayth that if he for his owne part ſhould haue taught any ſuch doctrine, he had beene wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to haue beene hanged vp in the market-place.</p>
            <p>But alas, this will not help them, for what reaſon had our learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour to take the paynes to ſearch whether they were <hi>Hoſius</hi> his wordes or no, it was ſufficient I hope for him to find them there, and ſo finding
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:762:11"/>
them, to take them, and ſtop the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts throtes with them in what ſenſe ſoeuer <hi>Hoſius</hi> ſpake them. I aſſure you this was done moſt eloquently, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpiritually, to make the Papiſts know, they deale with men of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and ſuch as know how to vexe a Papiſt, and delude their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; bring their owne beſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours agaynſt themſelues. This I aſſure you, Madame, is now all in all amogſt our learned Writers, &amp; I hope I haue plaied my part herin (as ſhalbe ſeen anone) as well as the beſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>But this Biſhop hath not left them ſo, I trow. No: he hath yet layd ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Red caps doctrine open, &amp; conſequently of theirs, to wit <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines.</hi> Although (ſayth Bellarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) <hi>the Bookes of the Apostles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets be diuine, yet ſhould I not certaynly belieue them, except I haue before hand belieued the Scripture: for alſo in ſundry places of Mahomets Alcaron we read that the ſame was of God from Heauen, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:762:12"/>
yet we do not belieue it.</hi> Thus M. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. But now behold M Doctour how wittily he catcheth this graue Cardinall in his owne trap. <hi>Orthodox. pag.</hi> 136. he makes the Cardinall ſay thus: <hi>A man is not bound to belieue the Scripture to be diuine, becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe ſayth ſo, more then one is bound to belieue the Alcaron to be of God, becauſe in many places thereof, we read that it was ſent from heauen of God.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould the excellency of this Doctors wit, how cunningly he reprehends the Cardinall of blaſphemy agaynſt the Word of God.</p>
            <p>O Madame, this is a thing that nips the Ieſuits to the hart, &amp; makes them ſcratch their heads to defend their Cardinall, &amp; behold when all is done what a poore ſhift they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly vnto. They are fayne to ſay forſooth, that this Reuerend Doctour is a moſt egregious lyar, and falſifier of <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Yes, forſooth, if we would follow their Counſell, <hi>D.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:762:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
White</hi> ſhould be forced to do Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and make reſtitution to <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> for his iniurious defamation, &amp; leauing out thoſe words, <hi>except I haue before hand belieued the Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I warrant you, the Doctour is wiſe inough, and we too. Weele haue nothing to do with their Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Reſtitutions; they are things as hatefull vnto vs, as the Maſſe it ſelfe. Let them count vs fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifiers, lyers, deceauers and the lyke, they ſhall find we are no ſuch men, but true zealous profeſſours of the Word, &amp; ſuch as know how to beat downe Popery, as well as the beſt. And as for the Biſhop himſelfe, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they alleadge he had his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke for lying, let them know that had he not ſold (as they ſay he hath) his library to rayſe his family, and prouide for his children, neuer to be ſtayned with the leaſt ſpot of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, he had anſwered the <hi>Nine-Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> long before this.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:762:13"/>Now Madame, crauing your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience (for I know your Goodnes will neuer thinke that time to long which is ſpent in reuewing the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty proceedings of our learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours) enter <hi>D. Morton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> for nimblenes of wit in this kind inferiour to none. None more taxed by the Wicked then he for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, lying, ſhifting, and falſify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in one Booke 600. But let them talke, he is rare in interpreting lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Authors, according to his owne ſenſe; he can make them ſpeake as pleaſes himſelfe; and for paying the Papiſts home with ſcoffes, taunts, &amp; ieſts none more excellent then he: and thus he is able to put the beſt of them to ſilence, with all their Scriptures, Fathers, and Authorities.</p>
            <p>One way of arguing I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him, and it is a rare one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to wit, to bring the Papiſts owne obiections for their ſolutions, as you may ſee in the 4. page of his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:762:13"/>
               <hi>Diſcouery,</hi> where he citeth a text of <hi>Gratiam, cauſa</hi> 15 <hi>cap.</hi> 99 <hi>gloſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>If I haue ſworne to pay any money to one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated after my oath, I am not bound to pay it him; the reaſon is, becauſe we ought to vexe euill men by what meanes ſoeuer, to the end they may ceaſe from doing ill.</hi> Where, if you marke, in theſe laſt wordes we haue authority by their own Authors to vexe them all we can, being a wicked people.</p>
            <p>Now it is true, that the words of of the Gloſſe contayne only an obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vpon that clauſe of the Canon concerning paying of money to an excommunicated perſon, &amp; the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection is made by the Authour of the Gloſſe in theſe wordes: <hi>What will you ſay, if I ſweare to pay one money &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he is excommunicated, am I bound to pay it, or no?</hi> Afterwards he argues the queſtion on both ſides, and then concludes, that the Debtour ought to pay the money, though the other cannot demaund it. Now, the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:762:14"/>
Biſhop to make the Papiſtes doctrine odious, leaueth out both the firſt wordes, that ſhew it is an obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the laſt, to wit, <hi>that ſuch a one is bound to pay it,</hi> which is the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and very wittily, he makes the ſentence go thus: <hi>If I haue ſworne to pay any one money that is excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, I am not bound to pay it.</hi> This was artificially done. Agayne he relateth that <hi>D. Boucher</hi> holdeth, that a King may be killed by a priuate ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when <hi>D. Boucher</hi> holdeth abſolutly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. This is to make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the Truth, and make them ſay that which they doe not; which is an honeſt, good, and profitable policy.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>Preamble pag.</hi> 90. he hath ſo zealous a hatred agaynſt the Pope, that he affirmeth with great ioye, that <hi>Adrian</hi> the Engliſh Pope was choked with a fly, &amp; citeth <hi>Nauclerus</hi> for it, who only doth mention it, as a fable, and refutes it.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Parſons</hi> haue proued E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:762:14"/>
in ſome caſes to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, both out of Scripture, euen by Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Io.</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. and <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes ſaying: Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech had neyther Father nor Mother; Toby</hi> the 5. that the Angell that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, calling himſelfe the ſonne of great <hi>Ananias,</hi> his name was <hi>Azarias:</hi> Theſe they ſay, were no lyes &amp;c. So Schoole Diuines out of <hi>Augustine in Pſal.</hi> 5. that albeyt a lye be vnlawfull, yet to conceale a truth it may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. So, many are brought by <hi>Parſons</hi> in his <hi>Mitigation,</hi> as to ſaue the life of a Prieſt. But what of all this? the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people neuer come to read this Booke of <hi>Parſons,</hi> or others of that ſide; and for the learned it ſtands the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon to concurre togeather, by all meanes to beat downe Papiſtry, and therfore the Biſhop cryed out: <hi>not one iote of Scripture, no one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no one reaso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the naturall wit of man, no one Authour Greeke or Latin do make for Equiuocation, as the Papiſts teach it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:762:15"/>So he alledgeth <hi>Azor</hi> a Ieſuit in his <hi>Preamble pag.</hi> 84. and 85. to condemne all vſe of Equiuocation, and that by fiue rules, but he leaueth out foure of the ſayd fiue rules, as directly agaynſt him, allowing in ſome caſes Equiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. In the ſame manner he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth another Ieſuit <hi>Emanuel Sà.</hi> Now to bring their owne Authors againſt them is both witty &amp; learned. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine hath not eſcaped him: and you may ſee, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by <hi>Parſons</hi> owne works, the <hi>Mitigation</hi> &amp; the <hi>Sober Reckoning,</hi> how rare a man Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> is.</p>
            <p>But I will end heer with this, that you may ſee how the Papiſts are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with this right worthy and true dealing Biſhop. For after great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſhew hundreds of lyes and corruptions, as they ſay; then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, they dare preſume to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him of ignorance, euen in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, ſhewing that his Syllogiſme is neyther true in matter or forme, but hath ſixe termes, and concludes no
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:762:15"/>
more then he which proueth the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Biſhop to be an Aſſe, if you will belieue the Papiſts:
<q>
                  <l>Euery Man is a liuing creature,</l>
                  <l>Euery Oxe is a foure-footed beaſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> euery Aſſe hath two lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g eares.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if this worthy and learned Doctour be thus abuſed by the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Crew, what muſt I expect? If he that ſtileth himſelfe, <hi>A Minister of ſimple Truth,</hi> in his <hi>Preamble,</hi> &amp; yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after (as they would ſhew) cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth <hi>Polidor Virgill;</hi> if this man be taxed, what will they doe to me his ſcholler, who haue imitated him &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as <hi>M. Perkins, Fulke, Bel, Sutcliffe, Iewel;</hi> &amp; others of my owne ranke, as <hi>Sir Edward Cooke, Hoby, Haſtings, Pleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Mornay,</hi> who all, with them, are notorious lyers. But for all this, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth a Knight to take courage, &amp; not to be daunted, and neuer to yield that there is the leaſt corruption in any of our Writings; for to confeſſe a fault, is rather Vility, then Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:762:16"/>
in our Religion.</p>
            <p>And therefore with the greateſt magnanimity of ſpirit will I begin to defend my ſelfe (relying vpon theſe a foreſayd Authours) that euer did noble knight. They taxe me with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lyes; but wil you know the cauſe? The truth is they are galled to ſee my workes, &amp; my ſelf ſo highly eſteemed for them, as I am indeed, &amp; I do glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify my ſelfe, and the Lord for it.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, with ſword and ſhield to defend my honour; they are much troubled with my 7. Section, becauſe in it I ſhew their pedigree from old Heretickes; and therefore I haue tould 9. or 10. lyes (ſay they.) Now what is the firſt I pray you? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Maſſe forſooth. And who would not labour to beate it downe, ſeeing the very Diuell himſelfe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it ſo much, that he taught <hi>D. Luther</hi> to write agaynſt it. But now to my Charges.</p>
            <div n="1" type="charge">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:762:16"/>
               <head>Firſt Charge.</head>
               <p>I ſayd, <hi>Vitalian</hi> the Pope that liued in the yeare 666. brought in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin ſeruice. They not enduring this, tell me to my face, that <hi>Gregory</hi> the great (who liued in the yeare 590. there being 11. Popes between him &amp; <hi>Vitalian</hi>) ſent the Latin ſeruice hither by <hi>Augustine</hi> the Monke: &amp; to make the matter more cleere, they bring <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his Sermon <hi>vpon the Lords Prayer,</hi> to affirme the ſame preface of the Maſſe to be ſayd in Latin, that is now ſayd. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book of <hi>Christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Doctrine ca.</hi> 13. in his booke <hi>de bono perſeuerantiae cap.</hi> 3. affirmeth, that in the Maſſe, after <hi>Habemus ad Dominum,</hi> preſently the Prieſt anſwereth, <hi>Gratias agamus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Deo nostro;</hi> and then followes, <hi>Dignum &amp; iuſtumest.</hi> Thus they bring their old Maſſe Prieſts againſt me for their owne Maſſe. Would any man haue made ſo ſimple an anſwere?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:762:17"/>Then they will conuince me with <hi>Iohn Stow,</hi> a good, honeſt, ſimple fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that in his Chronicle ſaith, that the Engliſh ſeruice began firſt in <hi>K. Edward</hi> the ſixt his dayes. Now, why ſhould not I anſwere with al my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Anceſtours? What is Cyprian? What is Auguſtine? Were they not men? What haue we to doe with them when they are againſt vs? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are for vs, we haue reaſon to vrge them agaynſt the Papiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they honour them, and relye vpon them, but not we; for we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to relye only vpon the Word of God according to our owne inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations. For we be more then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that the Lord will not ſuffer vs, the predeſtinate, to erre. Now it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me, that I may with <hi>D. Luther, Caluin, Fulke, D Humfrey,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the reformed Church, reiect the Fathers, not caring for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Augustins, Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp;c.</hi> And thus I anſwere for the Latin ſeruice, deſiring
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:762:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them to keep the Fathers to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, for we make no accompt of them. Now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a greater buſines about.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="charge">
               <head>The ſecond Charge.</head>
               <p>I ſayd, the Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation began in the <hi>Lateran Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> 400. yeares agoe. The Papiſts will haue it more ancient, ſaying, that my owne Maiſters will giue me the lye; &amp; that only the word (Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation) began then agaynſt <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius,</hi> who oppoſed the doctrine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councell, and therefore it was taught before: &amp; ſo they tell me that <hi>Iohn Foxe,</hi> a good honeſt dealing man (that hath tould but 1000. lyes in his Acts and Monuments, and 120. within the ſpace of three leaues) giues my Worſhip the Whetſtone, he might as well ſay, the lye. <hi>Iohn Foxe</hi> in the booke of his Acts printed 1576. <hi>pag.</hi> 1121. affirmeth the denying of <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> began to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herely 1060. and in that number
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:762:18"/>
was one <hi>Berengarius,</hi> who liued about the yeare 1060. Now, ſaith my Papiſt, what doth your Knightſhip ſay to the Fox? Marry I ſay, the Fox is a Gooſe, and deſerues to be hanged in chaines for not abuſing the Papiſts more in thoſe Primitiue tymes.</p>
               <p>Againe they bring <hi>D. Humfrey</hi> who ſaith: <hi>Gregory</hi> the great and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> brought <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: So he in his <hi>Ieſuitiſme</hi> 2. <hi>part. rat.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 626. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Beza,</hi> diſlikes <hi>S. Cyril</hi> for this doctrine. <hi>M. Whitgift</hi> in his defence againſt <hi>Cartwrights reply. pa.</hi> 408. ſaith <hi>Ignatius</hi> the diſciple of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſayd of the heretickes of thoſe times, they do not admit the Euchariſt to be the fleſh of our Sauiour Ieſus-Chriſt, which fleſh ſuffered for our ſinnes. Heere, he ſayth, he could bring the ancient Fathers, to change the name of <hi>Syr Humfrey Linde,</hi> into <hi>Syr Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey Lyes;</hi> ſo omitting, as he ſayth, the authority of Chriſt himſelfe in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:762:18"/>
the Fathers, Councels, and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of the old Teſtament, leaues me to conſider how true a Knight I am. And by this you may ſee how graceleſſe a Papiſt he is, to giue a Knight the lye.</p>
               <p>Yet he vrgeth me further &amp; ſayth, <hi>Iudas was the first of my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of Tranſubſtantiation: from him &amp; the Capharnaits Berengarius, and ſo from him Luther and Caluin, then to Grandſire Foxe, Father Morton, and ſo to his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship Syr Humfrey Lind: ſo Iudas was the roote, and the Knight cometh directly from his line.</hi> I confeſſe, this did put me into choller, in which I ſware that if I knew this Papiſt, he ſhould well know, that I am a Knight-figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as well as a Knight-writer, which few know of I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe. He promiſeth a more ample pedigree, but let him keep it to himſelfe, I deſire it not, I ſay I am wronged, and will reuenge it when, and where I can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="charge">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:762:19"/>
               <head>The third Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſayd <hi>Phocas</hi> was the firſt that gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted Supremacy to the Biſhop of <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stantinople,</hi> they make my Author <hi>Vrſpergenſis</hi> ſay, <hi>Rome.</hi> But let that paſſe. Agayne they ſay, he is corup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by vs, and that <hi>Phocas</hi> could not giue Supremacy, becauſe he neuer had any ſuch power, neyther could he be the firſt, ſeeing <hi>Iustinian</hi> ratified the Decrees &amp; Canons of the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, with an Edict, as all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Princes do now; So <hi>Phocas</hi> only ſet forth the Decrees. But my owne Maiſters will vexe me worſe (he ſaith.) <hi>M. Whitaker,</hi> and <hi>M. Fulke</hi> ſay, <hi>That Pope Victor was the first that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerciſed iuriſdiction ouer forrayne Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> ſo <hi>M. Whitaker agaynſt Duraeus lib</hi> 7. <hi>M. Fulke</hi> in his anſwer to a <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyt Catholicke pag.</hi> 36. <hi>And at this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the Church of Rome was in great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> (ſayth the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:762:19"/>
being neere to the Apostles, in the yeare</hi> 158. So Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> ſets forth <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> and the Church of Rome in thoſe daies. Thus with a bragge of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing me of an vntruth, and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me to Sciptures and Fathers, he ends this Charge.</p>
               <p>But I will not take ſo much pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſeeing I can haue a true Note<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke of a true Miniſter; where eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing is Featly ſet downe; their notes are my Scriptures and Fathers, vpon their wordes and credits I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, for I know they will not deceyue Me, though they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the Papiſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="charge">
               <head>The fourth Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſayd, the worſhip of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages was decreed by the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> almoſt 800. yeares ſince Chriſt; heere the Papiſts ſay, <hi>If I meane diuine worship, as my Rabbins teach out of the pulpit the ignorant people, then it is falſe, they haue no ſuch Doctrine: if
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:762:20"/>
I meane relatiuely, and tranſitorily with reſpect to the perſon it repreſents, as good ſubiects doe to the Chaire of State, with reference to his Maiesty, then I fayle of the tyme;</hi> for that <hi>Iſaurus</hi> oppoſed this doctrine before that Councell was aſſembled anno 726. and that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that tyme, as <hi>Damaſcene, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus,</hi> and others condemne this He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy of the <hi>Iconoclasts,</hi> which began by <hi>Iewes, Turkes, Saracens,</hi> and Heretiks, and is ſtill maintained by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and noble Knight <hi>Syr Humfrey Linde,</hi> agaynſt Chriſt, and all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers: And by moſt of the Engliſh Clergy, as appeared lately in <hi>Starre-chamber (an.</hi> 1633.) there was granted the pious vſe of them; &amp; the Papiſts haue not any other in them, and ſo they tell me, <hi>the Councell conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Hereſy, not decreed the doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But who knoweth not, that we diſclayme from their Councels? For as <hi>D. Luther</hi> truly ſayd, <hi>art.</hi> 115. <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels are but as Parlaments of Princes, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:762:20"/>
what is defyned by them, is ſubiected to the Iudgement of euery priuate man. It is a mad thing that what a Councell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth should be belieued, ſeeing what is to be belieued and what not, is left to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpirituall mans iudgment, and ſo fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well all Councels and Fathers. Giue me the pure word, and a pure ſpirit that knoweth only what bookes are Canonicall.</hi> This is the doctrine of <hi>D. Luther,</hi> &amp; <hi>D. Caluin</hi> which I follow, and ſo my Spirit is with theirs; and ſo I hope I haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered their Councells and Fathers ſufficiently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="charge">
               <head>The fifth Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I tell them, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>cap.</hi> 3. ſayth, that the <hi>Baſilidians</hi> and <hi>Carpocratians</hi> worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Images, and from them I deriue their pedigree: The firſt of theſe, ſay the Papiſts, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> witneſſeth, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Images and Inchantements, but maketh no mention of worſhip. Of the later they ſay, they had the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:762:21"/>
of Chriſt, but honoured it as the Heathens did their Idols, &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it togeather with the Images of <hi>Pluto, Pythagoras, Aristotle,</hi> and vſed them as Gentiles doe: So that heere he ſayth I haue groſly abuſed them, &amp; belyed <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and that I agree with the <hi>Baſilidians</hi> &amp; <hi>Carpocratians</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny points of my Religion. But he wil proue this when I haue defended my ſelfe, and cleered my ſelf of this falſe dealing, which will neuer be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="charge">
               <head>The ſixth Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſay, <hi>the Communion in one kind was decreed by the Councell of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stance aboue</hi> 1400. <hi>yeares after Chriſt,</hi> the lye was told long ſince (ſay they) by my Father <hi>Luther,</hi> as <hi>Card. Bellarm.</hi> noteth <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Eucharist cap.</hi> 26. <hi>M. Craſhaw</hi> and others haue it; ſo that it is a ſtale lye, and they find great fault becauſe he citeth Authours that the whole world eſteemeth lyers, as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay Pleſsis</hi> who is conuinced of 4000.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:762:21"/>
lyes (a goodly company) a man no doubt of great zeale, and of a braue Spirit: for being vrged with theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths before the King of <hi>France,</hi> his ſtomake was ſo full, that he caſt it vp euen in the Papiſts faces, and in the very preſence of the King of <hi>France Henry</hi> the IV. this I ſay, was a true Romane, a braue Spirit, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Anceſtours ſhined in him.</p>
               <p>Heere my Papiſt intreates me to read <hi>Parſons three Conuerſions,</hi> for that I may learne to lye out of <hi>M. Foxe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mornay Pleſsis,</hi> both whom are painted forth in their owne true colours; But I ſcorne to read <hi>Parſons,</hi> or to learne to lye of any man, neither <hi>Parſon</hi> nor Miniſter ſhall teach me to lye. And heer alſo the wonderfull Papiſt falles into a wonder at me, for wrangling about the Cup, ſeeing my owne Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins haue depriued me both of Cup &amp; Sacrament, meat and drinke too.</p>
               <p>He is angry likewiſe becauſe I cite not the place in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell; but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:762:22"/>
for that I haue my reaſons. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth that there is any ſuch thing in the Councell; but only in the 13. Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion there are theſe wordes: <hi>Though Christ did institute the Venerable Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after ſupper, and administred the ſame in both kinds to his diſciples, yet the laudable authority of ſacred Canons, and approued Cuſtoms of the Church hath pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, and doth ſtill practiſe, that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ought not to be conſecrated after ſupper, nor be receyued of the faithfull but faſting.</hi> And ſo cals to me for a Decree as though I were bound to cite pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at his pleaſure: and like a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Iacke he ſaith, that in this point we may be termed the <hi>giddy builders of Babilon,</hi> ſo great is our diſſention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Euchariſt.</p>
               <p>And for the Communion in both kindes, or one kind, it was left to the iudgement of the Church; and that life eternall is promiſed for ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one kind, and ſo Chriſt himſelfe gaue it. He ſayth he will not ſtand to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:762:22"/>
cite places of Scripture, ſeeing that I belieue neuer a word in the Scripture and that he were better deale with an Infidell, then with an obſtinate here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke. And that, I with all my Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity cannot diſtinguiſh betweene a Diuine Inſtitution, &amp; a Diuine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: for though he inſtituted it in both kindes, yet he commanded it not to be receaued in both kinds; for many things are inſtituted, yet not commanded, as Matrimony &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if I loathed wine (as he heares I do not) he doth not doubt to get me a diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to waſh downe the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord with a Cup of good March beere, or Ale. For my vntruth in this matter I muſt looke vpon <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus Regius</hi> a learned man of our owne, who confeſſeth that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of one kind was ordained in the firſt Councell of <hi>Epheſus</hi> 1000. yeares before the Synod of <hi>Constance,</hi> for the extinguiſhing the <hi>Nestorian</hi> hereſy, who held the body to be without the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:762:23"/>
bloud in one kind, &amp; the bloud to be without the body in another kind: but the Knight, ſaith he, holdeth it in neyther kind, and therfore but kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt withall, to haue his kind ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhewed to the whole Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his learned Brethren, that may giue him better counſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="charge">
               <head>The VII. Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I affirme in my 7. Section, that the heretickes <hi>Angelici</hi> were the firſt founders of praying to Saints, I cite for this <hi>Aug. lib. de haereſ.</hi> who (the Papiſtes ſay) <hi>doth not ſo much as name Saints in that place by me cited:</hi> and that it is a plaine iugling trick to bring <hi>Augustin</hi> againſt that doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne which the world knoweth he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as it is ſeene in his <hi>Meditations cap.</hi> 40. <hi>S. Michael, S. Gabriel, S. Raphael ſupplicate for me.</hi> Now, ſay they, theſe <hi>Angelici,</hi> held that Angels were to be adored as Gods, or that they thought Angels made the world, or that they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:762:23"/>
boaſted that they liued Angelicall ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and therefore placed themſelues in the Order of Angels: from hence they had their name, &amp; from hence <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> numbers them among He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes; &amp;, ſay the Papiſts, <hi>they num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Knight amongst them for his Via tuta;</hi> this is becauſe I haue layd out their wicked doctrine, but I promiſe to make them more odious if I can.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Collyridians, S. Aug.</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds them for honouring the bleſſed Virgin as a Goddeſſe, &amp; not for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring her as Catholiks do; &amp; ſo out of his authority bids me, <hi>learne the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene Idolatry, and honouring the friends and Saints of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="charge">
               <head>The VIII. Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I deriue their doctrine of <hi>Merit,</hi> &amp; <hi>works of ſuperogation</hi> from the <hi>Cathari;</hi> this (ſay they) is as true as the reſt; for they boaſted of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as I &amp; Puritans do; that the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thari</hi> &amp; I agree in 16. Points; they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:762:24"/>
Penna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as the Knight doth; &amp; although Scripture threaten death eternall to thoſe that do not pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nance, yet they Knight wil none. <hi>Nouatianus</hi> the Captaine of the <hi>Cathari</hi> made his followers take a ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne oath that they would neuer returne to the Pope who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was <hi>Cornelius;</hi> ſo hath the Knight ſworne to hate the Pope &amp;c. which I deny not, and I loue the <hi>Cathari</hi> the better for their zeale.</p>
               <p>Now, for the <hi>Merit,</hi> they ſay, <hi>there is no mention of it, but of their hypocriſy:</hi> &amp; for their doctrine of good Works, they ſend me to learne, for that there are many things belonging to make a good worke merito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious in the ſight of God. I haue bin often taught (they ſay) &amp; therfore they will not ſtand to repeate my leſſon to me agayne, but ſend me to their learned Authours. Neyther will I ſpend tyme to learne their doctrine which I hate, &amp; ſo I do all their good Works, vowing neuer to do any while I liue for their ſakes:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:762:24"/>
for in this I am of <hi>D. Luthers</hi> mind, to be oppoſite to the Pope in all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="charge">
               <head>The IX. Charge.</head>
               <p>Becauſe I ſay the reſtraint of their Prieſts marriage was the hereſy of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> &amp; the <hi>Maniches,</hi> for which I cite <hi>haereſ.</hi> 46. they Papiſts ſay, <hi>that Tatians hereſy was for denyall of marriages, and comparing them with fornication: neyther would he receiue any into his Sect that was marryed;</hi> &amp; there is not one ſillable of the marriage of Prieſts, &amp; that all the Papiſts condemne this for hereſy, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding marriage a Sacrament. That of the <hi>Maniches</hi> was another moſt abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Hereſy: <hi>for they vſing matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall acts, yet most ſinnefully ſhunned Conception:</hi> So <hi>Aug. haereſ.</hi> 46. &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I am a moſt true dealing Knight which is more praiſe then I deſerue.</p>
               <p>The Papiſt in a letter to me, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo Nine Falſifications of <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> in my <hi>Via tuta,</hi> and might haue done many more but that it was tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to him; I deſired him not to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:762:25"/>
trouble himſelfe with making theſe: but it is no matter, for I hope to ſhew that I haue cited <hi>Bellarmine</hi> truly, &amp; to teach the Papiſts to be wary how they write bookes againſt a Knight; for ſhortly I will put forth a Booke that ſhall vtterly diſgrace both Pope and Papiſts: and this the ſooner, if I ſhall heare that your La<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. is ſatisfyed by this Letter, &amp; thereby alſo to anſwer for me to thoſe ſcoffing Neutraliſts.</p>
               <p>And ſo, Right Honourable, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring euer to be eſteemed one of your Seruants, and one I hope that ſhalbe ready in this kind, againſt all Papiſts, to do you Knights Seruice, I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Honours Seruant, euer ready to dye in your quarrell, &amp; for the truth of the pure Word. <hi>H. Linde.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:762:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
